<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>His Majesties most gracious speech, together with the Lord Chancellors, to both Houses of Parliament, on Wednesday the 30th of April, 1679. By His Majesties special command</title>
            <title>Speeches. 1679-04-30</title>
            <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1660-1685 : Charles II)</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1679</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 6 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A79270</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C3187</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R223887</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99896936</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99896936</idno>
            <idno type="VID">135645</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A79270)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 135645)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2457:22)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>His Majesties most gracious speech, together with the Lord Chancellors, to both Houses of Parliament, on Wednesday the 30th of April, 1679. By His Majesties special command</title>
                  <title>Speeches. 1679-04-30</title>
                  <author>England and Wales. Sovereign (1660-1685 : Charles II)</author>
                  <author>Charles II, King of England, 1630-1685.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>7, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>re-printed by the heir of Andrew Anderson, printer to His most sacred Majesty,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>anno Dom. 1679.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library, Washington, D.C.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Popish Plot, 1678 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Charles II, 1660-1685 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:135645:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 13 -->
            <p>His Majeſties Moſt Gracious SPEECH, Together with the Lord
  Chancellor's, To both Houſes of PARLIAMENT, on <hi>Wedneſday</hi> the
  30<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>April,</hi> 1679.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By His Majeſties ſpecial Command.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>EDINBURGH,</hi> Re-Printed by the Heir of <hi>Andrew
  Anderſon,</hi> Printer to His moſt Sacred <hi>MAJESTY, Anno Dom.</hi>
  1679.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="speech">
            <pb facs="tcp:135645:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 14 -->
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:135645:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 15 -->
            <head>His Majeſties Moſt Gracious SPEECH To both Houſes of
  PARLIAMENT, On <hi>Wedneſday</hi> the 30<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of <hi>April.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>  
               <salute>My Lords and Gentlemen,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Seaſon of the Year advancing ſo faſt, I thought it
  neceſſary to put you in mind of Three Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars:</p>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>1. Proſecution of the Plot.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2. Disbanding the Army.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3. Providing a Fleet for Our common
 Security.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>And to ſhew you that whilſt you are doing 
  <pb n="4" facs="tcp:135645:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 16 -->your Parts, My thoughts have
  not been miſ-imploy'd, but that it is My constant Care to do every thing that
  may preſerve your Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and ſecure it for the future in all Events; I
  have Commanded my Lord Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor to mention ſeveral Particulars, which I
  hope will be an Evidence, that in all things that concerns the Publique
  Security, I ſhall not follow your Zeal, but lead it.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="speech">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:135645:4"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 16 -->
            <head>THE Lord Chancellor's SPEECH To both Houſes of
  PARLIAMENT.</head>
            <opener>  
               <salute>
                  <hi>My Lords, and you the Knights, Citizens, and
 Burgeſſes of the Houſe of Commons,</hi>
               </salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat Royal Care which His Majeſty hath taken for the General
  Quiet and Satisfaction of all His Subjects, is now more Evident by theſe New
  and freſh Inſtances of it which I have in Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand to open to You.</p>
            <p>His Majeſty hath Conſider'd with Himſelf, That 'tis not
  Enough that your Religion and Liberty is ſecure during His own Reign, but He
  thinks He ows it to his People to do all that in Him Lies, that theſe
  Bleſſings may be tranſmitted to your Poſterity, and ſo well ſecur'd
  to them, that no Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion in after Ages may be able to work the Leaſt
  Alteration.</p>
            <p>And therefore His Majeſty, who hath often ſaid in this
  Place, That he is ready to conſent to any Laws of this Kind, ſo as the
  ſame Extend not to alter the Deſcent of the Crown in the Right Line, nor to
  Defeat the Succeſſion, hath now Commanded this to be further Explain'd.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:135645:5"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 17 -->
            <p>And to the End it may never be in the Power of any Papiſt, if
  the Crown Deſcend upon him, to make any Change either in Church or State, I
  am Commanded to tell you, That His Majeſty is willing that Proviſion may be
  made, Firſt to Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſh a Popiſh from a Proteſtant Succeſſor,
  Then ſo to Limit and to Circumſcribe the Authority of a Popiſh
  Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor in theſe Caſes following, that he may be diſabled to do
  any Harm.</p>
            <p>Firſt in Reference to the Church, His Majeſty is content
  that Care be taken that all Eccleſiaſtical and Spiritual Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices and
  Promotions in the Gift of the Crown, may be Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferr'd in ſuch a Manner, that
  we may be ſure the Incumbents ſhall always be of the moſt Pious and
  Learned Proteſtants; And that no Popiſh Succeſſor, while he continues
  ſo, may have any power to Controll ſuch Preſentments.</p>
            <p>In Reference to the State and Civil part of the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, As
  it is already Provided that no Papiſt can Sit in either Houſe of
  Parliament, So the King is pleaſed that it be provided too, that there may
  never want a Parliament when the King ſhall happen to Die, but that the
  Parliament then in being may Continue Indiſſoluble for a Competent Time, Or
  if there be no Parliament in being, then the Laſt Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment which was in
  being before that time may Re-aſsemble and Sit a Competent Time without any
  new Summons or Elections.</p>
            <p>And as no Papiſt can by Law hold any Place of Truſt, ſo
  the King is content that it may be further Provided that no Lords or others of
  the Privy-Council, No Judges of the Common-Law, or in Chancery, ſhall at any
  time during the Raign of any Popiſh Succeſsor be put in or diſplaced but
  by the Authority of Parliament. And care alſo be taken that none but
  ſincere Proteſtants may be Juſtices of Peace.</p>
            <p>In Reference to the Military Part, The King is willing that no
  Lord Lieutenant, or Deputy Lieutenant, nor no Officer in the Navy during the
  Raign of any Popiſh Succeſsor be <pb n="7" facs="tcp:135645:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 18 -->put
  in or remov'd but either by Authority of Parliament, or of ſuch Perſons as
  the Parliament ſhall entruſt with ſuch Authority.</p>
            <p>'Tis hard to invent another reſtraint to be put upon a
  Popiſh Succeſsor, Conſidering how much the Revenue of the Succeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor
  will depend upon conſent of Parliament, and how Impoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible it is to
  raiſe Money without ſuch conſent. But yet if any thing elſe can Occur
  to the Wiſdom of the Parliament, which may further Secure Religion and
  Liberty againſt a Popiſh Succeſsor, without Defeating the Right of
  Succeſſion it ſelf, His Majeſty will moſt readily conſent to
  it.</p>
            <p>Thus Watchful is the King for all your Safeties, and if He could
  think of any thing elſe that you do either Want or Wiſh to make you Happy,
  He would make it His buſineſs to Effect it for you.</p>
            <p>God Almighty Long Continue this Bleſſed Union between the
  King and his Parliament and People.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
